Finding Aid for Grant K Goodman papers, 1943-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Grant K Goodman papers 1943-1995
Goodman, Grant Kohn
0.5 linear feet
0336 Aa 2
Grant K. Goodman was a student at the University of Michigan's Army Intensive Japanese Language School (AIJLS) during World War II. Goodman was the primary organizer of several AIJLS class reunions in the late 1980s and early 1990s. The collection contains papers documenting the AIJLS, specifically the Second Class, 1943-1944. It includes educational materials, reports, and commencement programs, as well as materials from the School's 1943 production of the musical "Nips in the Bud." A significant portion of the collection is made up of photographs, depicting life at AIJLS, Fort McClellan, Alabama, and in post-surrender Japan. Also included are materials related to Goodman's organization of the AIJLS reunions, largely comprised of correspondence, various written recollections, and a collection of six videocassettes.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials were received from Grant Goodman in 1997 and 2010. (donor no. 8647 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Grant Kohn Goodman was a student at the University of Michigan's Army Intensive Japanese Language School (AIJLS) from 1943 to 1944. The AIJLS was created by the United States War Department in order to build an elite corps of Japanese-speaking officers, who were to do intelligence work and provide support for combat troops. The school was an intensive course, consisting of intensive Japanese language and culture classes, as well as military drills, inspections, and typical army exercises characteristic of U.S. military training camps.
Goodman's class (Company A, 3651st Service Unit), graduated from AIJLS on January 4, 1944, and continued on to complete further training at the Military Intelligence Service Language School in Minnesota (MISLS). There, they underwent courses in the more technical and complicated aspects of intelligence work, and graduated on November 18, 1944. The soldiers were then sent to basic training at Fort McClellan in Alabama, and went on to join combat units in China, Burma, India, New Guinea, the Philippines, Australia, and Hawaii, where they served as translators and interrogators for Japanese prisoners of war. After the surrender, most of the AIJLS graduates became part of the Japanese occupation forces.
After the war Goodman returned to the University of Michigan where he received his masters degree in Far Eastern Studies under Professor Joseph Yamagiwa in 1939 and a PHD.
Goodman worked as a professor of Japanese history at the University of Kansas for thirty years, and spent time in the late 1980s and early 1990s at the International Research Center for Japanese Studies in Kyoto, Japan.
Goodman is the author of "Amerika no Nippon Gannen (America's Japan: The First Year)", published in 1990.
Goodman was instrumental in organizing reunions for students in the first two AIJLS courses at Ann Arbor. In May 1990 the last major reunion of the Ann Arbor AIJLS students was held in Ann Arbor.
The Grant K. Goodman collection documents the establishment and daily operations of the Army Intensive Japanese Language School (AIJLS), operating on the University of Michigan campus during World War II, as well as Goodman's later efforts to organize AIJLS reunions. The files are divided into seven series, and consist of papers, photographs and AV materials: Army Intensive Japanese Language School, Correspondence, "Nips in the Bud," Photographs, Publicity, "Random Recollections of the Second Class, AIJLS", and Videotapes.
Subjects:
United States. Army. Japanese Language School (University of Michigan); Goodman, Grant K.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor
Subjects - Visual Materials:
United States. Army. Japanese Language School (University of Michigan); World War, 1939-1945 -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor; Tokyo.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
United States. Army. Japanese Language School (University of Michigan); Nips in the Bud.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotates.
- Army Intensive Japanese Language School (AIJLS)
  The Army Intensive Japanese Language School papers encompass three years of the operation of the AIJLS, and include educational materials, commencement programs and an "AIJLS Day" proclamation by the mayor of Ann Arbor in 1990. Educational materials include reports on "Amenities in the Japanese Armed Forces" and "Japanese Methods of Prisoner of War Interrogation". These papers date from 1944 to 1990.
  - AIJLS Day Proclamation (and reunion material), 1990 (Box 1)
  - Commencement, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Research Reports (Allied Translator and Interpreter Section)
    - Amenities in the Japanese Armed Forces (photocopy), 1946 (Box 1)
    - Glossary of Japanese Medical Terms, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Japanese Methods of Prisoner of War Interrogation, 1946 (Box 1)
    - List of Japanese Personal Names with Unusual Readings, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Ryakuji -- Abbreviated Characters, 1944 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence consists mainly of letters between Goodman and various AIJLS alumni regarding the organization of AIJLS class reunions from 1988 to 1993.
  - 1988-1990 (Box 1)
- "Nips in the Bud"
  "Nips in the Bud" contains materials relating to a musical put on by AIJLS students (Company A, 3651st Service Unit) in 1943. It includes performance programs and song lyrics, as well as a cassette tape recording of the musical's War Bond performance on Sept. 30, 1943.
  - Programs and Recording, 1943 (Box 1)
- Publicity
  The Publicity series contains various newspaper and magazine articles covering both the history of the AIJLS and the class reunion organized by Goodman. The series covers the period between 1988 and 1993.
  - 1988-1993 (Box 1)
- "Random Recollections of the Second Class, AIJLS"
  "Random Recollections of the Second Class, AIJLS", compiled by Donald M. Richardson, was written in 1988 and thoroughly documents his memories of his time in AIJLS.
  - September 1988 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains photographs depicting life in the AIJLS on the University of Michigan campus, Goodman's experiences at Fort McClellan, and the American occupational forces in post-surrender Japan.
  - AIJLS, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Fort McClellan, Alabama, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Portrait, Miscellaneous, Ernie Pyle Theater (Box 1)
    - NYK Building, Tokyo, GHQ, SCAP, officer's Club (Box 1)
    - Tokyo, Candids, Train Station (Box 1)
    - AIJLS Inspection, 1943 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan (Box 1)
  - AIJLS Reunion, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Rackham Hall Group Photograph, 1943 (Box 1)
- Videotapes
  The Videotapes series consists of six videocassettes including footage recorded at the 1990 AIJLS class reunion and a 1994 documentary. produced by Japanese television station NHK title "Does This Streetcar Go to Hibiya?" Some of the tapes appear to be duplicates.
  - Company A Classes of 1943-1945/U.S. Army Intelligence Part One (Box 1)
  - Company A Classes of 1943-1945/U.S. Army Intelligence Part Two (Box 1)
  - Tape #1, Reunion: 1990 Does This Streetcar Go to Hibiya? NHK 1994, vhs, 50 minutes (Box 1)
  - Tape #2, Reunion: Is This Streetcar for Hibiya? NHK-E Channel 3, August 26, 1994, vhs (Box 1)
  - Tape #3 GKG-Sunflower Cable-7 Aug 95 / 2) Reunion-Streetcar to Hibiya-8 Aug 95 / 3) Tokyo Rose--Biography, vhs (Box 1)
  - Tape #4 (unidentified, NHK promo?), vhs (Box 1)